Register of the Vervon Orval Watts papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vervon Orval Watts papers
1920-1983
83064
Hoover Institution Archives
24 manuscript boxes (9.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, notes, instructional materials, research materials, clippings, and other printed matter relating to economic conditions in the United States and economic theory, especially laissez-faire economics.
Watts, Vervon Orval, 1898-1993
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1983.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1898 March 25 Born, Manitoba, Canada
1918 Graduated from University of Manitoba
1923 M.A., Harvard University
post-1923 Ph.D., Harvard University
circa 1925-1939 Taught at various colleges and universities, including Clark University, Harvard University, Wellesley, Antioch College, Carlton College, Claremont Men's College, Pepperdine University, and Campbell College
1938 Author, Why Are We So Prosperous?
1939 Economic counsel, Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce
1944 Author, Do We Want Free Enterprise?
1946 Editorial director, Foundation for Economic Education (FEE)
1952 Author, Away From Freedom
1954 Author, Union Monopoly
1955 Author, United Nations: Planned Tyranny
1963-1984 Director of economic education and chairman of the Division of Social Studies, Northwood University
1967 Author, Free Markets or Famine
1976 Author, Politics vs. Prosperity
1993 Died, Palm Springs, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The Vervon Orval Watts papers document the life and career of a conservative economist, academic, and opinion maker. An early critic of the New Deal, Watts maintained a lifelong commitment to laissez-faire principles, opposing government intervention in the economy and most social welfare programs. He sought to popularize these ideas by communicating them to a broad audience. His papers are largely comprised of writings, research materials, writings by others, and printed matter.
The extensive Speeches and Writings series contains many of Watts' articles, speeches, and pamphlets, as well as several monographs that he wrote or edited. The series also includes work that Watts did as a publicist and speechwriter for the Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce, including the texts of many lectures that he gave. The collection also has an extensive Subject File, comprised largely of clippings and articles, that reflects Watts' many research interests. Prior to serving as an economic advisor to organizations, Watts had a long teaching career, and the Academic File contains course materials, lecture notes, and syllabi relating to classes he taught at several institutions. Additionally, the academic file has a number of materials from Watts' time as a student, including papers that he wrote, as well as reading and lecture notes.
The collection also has a significant number of Speeches and Writings by Others, mainly on economic issues. There are also many pamphlets collected by Watts in the Printed Matter series, largely written by conservative authors.
Economics.; Economists.; Laissez-faire.; United States--Economic conditions.
- Biographical File, 1940, 1944
  - Certificate of appreciation, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Clipping, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Flyer, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Correspondence, 1922-1983
  - General, 1931-1974
    - A-F, 1937-1974 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - G-K, 1937-1961 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - L-P, 1931-1959 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Q-Z, 1937-1961 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Letters to the editor, 1935-1960 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Unidentified, 1935-1960 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - American Provident Society, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Anti-Defamation League, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Ayres, Leonard P., 1933 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Babcock, Mary Elizabeth, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Bell, Charles R., 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Binkley, Harold, 1923 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Blumenthal, Sidney, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Braden, Spruille, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Buck, Walter H., 1945 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Buffet, Howard, 1947 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Call, Joseph L., 1957-1958 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Carver, T. N., 1941-1947 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Chodorov, Frank, 1947 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Clise, J. W., 1957-1959 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Congress of Freedom, Inc., 1959 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Courtney, William H., 1950 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Cowling, Donald J., 1961 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Crane, George W., 1958-1961 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Crane, Jasper E., 1961 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Davis, Ralph, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Edwards, Le Roy M., 1943 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Fairchild, Fred Rogers, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Fick, Samuel L., 1944 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - Freedom School, Inc., 1958-1961 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - Fulton, James A., 1949 (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Gipson, J. H., 1945-1957 (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - Hart, Merwin K., 1957-1958 (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - Hart, William, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Hazlitt, Henry, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - Hiestand, Edgar W., 1958-1961 (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Hodgson, R. T., 1945 (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - Hoff, Trygve J. B., 1946-1949 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Hoiles, R. C., 1955-1959 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Johnson, Fred H., 1958 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Jones, Frederick W., 1946 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Kershner, Howard E., 1955-1959 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Kohlberg, Alfred, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Kooser, Ernest O., 1945 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Kuchel, Thomas H., 1961 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Lane, Rose Wilder, 1944-1957 (Box-folder 2: 9-10)
  - LeFevre, Robert, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Lombard, Norman, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Lowe, Dorothy, 1922-1924 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Luten, Daniel B., 1936 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - MacArthur, Harold, 1961 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Macbeth, Norman, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Mann, William D., 1957-1961 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Marion, Guy E., 1939 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Maughmer, G. F., 1946 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Mickey, Karl B., 1945 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Mullendore, William C., 1944-1952 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Murata, Toshio, 1958 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Nystrom, Paul H., 1943 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Pew, J. Howard, 1961 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Phillips, Charles W., 1945 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Radcliffe, Harry S., 1945 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Rapp, Robert, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Read, Leonard E., 1942-1955 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Retail Controllers Association, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Richardson, Annice, 1955 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Robb, John C., 1958 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Rogers, Robert G., 1958 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Rorty, M. C., 1933-1934 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Russell, John Henry, 1961 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Saxon, O. Glenn, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Schwarz, Fred, 1983 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Sexson, Paul A., 1944 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Shamer, G. P., 1955 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Shelly, Thomas J., 1958 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Shelton, James E., 1946 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Sheppard, G. A., 1958 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Sheridan, J. Paul, 1958 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Slaton, John M., 1945 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Smith, Walter B., 1951 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Smoot, Dan, 1957 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Southern California Edison Co., 1951 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Spahr, Walter E., 1958 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Spurgeon, W. H., Jr., 1958 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Stephens, Guy C., 1945 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Thompson, Joseph S., 1945 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Trippet, Oscar A., 1945 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Turner, W. Homer, 1958 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Untereiner, Ray E., 1943-1945 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - Watts, Mr. (father), undated (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Winans, Paul, 1946 (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - Wright, John S., 1945 (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - Young, Clyde L., 1937-1944 (Box-folder 3: 25)
- Speeches and Writings, 1930-1983
  - Columns
    - Christian Economics, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 3: 26)
    - Southern California Business Review, 1939-1941 (Box-folder 3: 27-28)
    - Yellow Springs News, 1932-1936 (Box-folder 3: 29)
  - "The American Mollusk,", undated (Box-folder 3: 30)
  - Article on banking, undated (Box-folder 3: 31)
  - Article on communism, undated (Box-folder 3: 32)
  - Article on interest rates and production, undated (Box-folder 3: 33)
  - Article on mass production, undated (Box-folder 3: 34)
  - "Buying Power Must Circulate,", undated (Box-folder 3: 35)
  - "Economic Rehabilitation,", undated (Box-folder 3: 36)
  - "An Economist's Reaction to the Proposals of Wm. P. Hapgood,", undated (Box-folder 3: 37)
  - "Fallacies,", undated (Box-folder 3: 38)
  - "Keynesism or Keynesianism,", undated (Box-folder 3: 39)
  - "Money and Free Markets,", undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - "An Old, Old Story!,", undated (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - "Principles of Economics,", undated (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - "On Selfishness and Progress,", undated (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - "Social Inequality,", undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Speech on agriculture, undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - "We Are Paying the Bill Now!,", undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - "What Price Inflation?,", undated (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - "When Enterprise Was a Privilege,", undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Writing on economics, undated (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Article on international payments, 1930 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - "A Defense of Capitalism,", 1930 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - "When Will Prices Stop Rising?,", 1933 June 24 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - "Capital and Wages,", 1936 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - "The Meaning of Freedom,", 1936 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - "New Deal Bureaucracy,", 1936 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - "The Significance of the Republican Convention,", 1936 (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - "The Tennessee Valley Authority,", 1936 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - "Technics and Civilization,", 1936 January (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - "The New Deal and the Negro,", 1936 June 8 (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - "Government and the People,", 1936 June 26 (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - "Liberalism,", 1936 June 26 (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - "The New Deal and Freedom,", 1936 June 26 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - "The President's 'Cure' for Unemployment,", 1936 June 26 (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - "Spiritual and Moral Aspects of Business ('Material') Prosperity,", 1936 June 26 (Box-folder 4: 25)
  - Writing on Karl Marx, 1937 January 24 (Box-folder 4: 26)
  - Finding Words for Common Sense, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 27)
  - Why Are We So Prosperous?, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 28-29)
  - "The Ham-and-Eggers Call It 'The Banana-Peel Movement,'", 1939 (Box-folder 4: 30)
  - "Ham-and-Eggers Know Their 'Warrants' Will Be 'Hot,'", 1939 (Box-folder 4: 31)
  - "Some Hurdles for the Economics Teacher,", 1939 February (Box-folder 4: 32)
  - Article on inequality and Henry Wallace, 1940 (Box-folder 4: 33)
  - Lecture outlines, Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce, 1940 (Box-folder 4: 34)
  - Report of the Committee on Production for Use, 1940 (Box-folder 4: 35)
  - "War Lessons for the United States,", 1940 May (Box-folder 4: 36)
  - "Discussion,", 1941 December (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Article on price fixing, 1942 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - "Price Freezing,", 1942 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - "Prospects for New Industries in Southern California,", 1942 July (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - "The New Deal-Nature and Origins,", 1943 March 12 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - "Post-war Boom or Collapse," lecture outline, 1943 July 19 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - "Post-war Boom or Depression?,", 1943 December (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - The Twilight of Free Enterprise, 1944 November 2 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - "Free Enterprise Is Free,", 1945 April (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - "Robin Hood Economics Not What the United States Wants,", 1945 April (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Remarks, 1945 May 13 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - "Promoting Communism through Currency Inflation,", 1945 June 19 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Article on housing shortage, 1946 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - "So You Believe in Rent Control?,", 1946 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - "Writer Scores Silly Tommy-Rot of Communism,", 1946 February (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - "Terminate Price Control,", 1946 March (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - "Collectivist Fallacies," speech outline, 1946 March 12 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - "Dealing with Collectivism,", 1946 June 17 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - "Mr. Dewey's Farm Program,", 1948 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - "Money, Currencies, and Credit in Free Markets,", 1950 (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - Lectures, Southern California Edison Co., 1950 (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - "Capitalism,", 1950 March 25 (Box-folder 5: 22)
  - Away from Freedom, 1952 Winter (Box-folder 5: 23)
  - "Hönan och guldäggen,", 1954 (Box-folder 5: 24)
  - The United Nations: Road to War, 1955 Spring (Box-folder 5: 25)
  - "When Will Prices Stop Rising?,", 1957 June 24 (Box-folder 5: 26)
  - "Recent Developments of New Economic Theories Relevant to Problems of Public Policy: Keynesian Economics,", 1960 (Box-folder 5: 27)
  - "When Enterprise Was a Privilege,", 1960 (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
  - Should We Strengthen the United Nations?, 1961 Winter (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Economize-or Perish!, 1964 Winter (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - "As a Man Thinks...,", 1965 December (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - "Away from Freedom,", 1966 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - "Why Humans Must Be Free,", 1966 March (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Free Markets or Famine, 1967, 1974
    - 1967 edition (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - 1974 edition (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - "From Sovereign Governments to Sovereign Individuals,", 1967 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Hunger Need Not Be, 1967 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Reactions to President Nixon's Address to the Nation, 1969 November 3 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - "John Steinbeck's The Grapes of Wrath: Marxian Ideology Wrapped in Obscenity,", 1970 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - "The 'New Economics' and Marxian Socialism,", 1971 March 21 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - "Are Schools Necessary?,", 1971 July (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - "The Northwood Idea,", 1973 March (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - "Industrialism: Friend or Foe?,", 1973 April (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - "Closing the Generation Gap,", 1973 July (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - "Business and Its Image,", 1974 July (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - "Diplomas versus Education,", 1975 (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - "The Law,", 1975 August (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - "Capitalism: Definition-Origins-Dynamics,", 1975 October (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - "Moral Law and Freedom,", 1976 January (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - Politics vs. Prosperity, 1978 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - "The Economics and Politics of Inflation,", 1983 March (Box-folder 8: 2)
- Transcripts, 1941-1942
  Scope and Contents note
  "Common Sense Hour" radio programs.
  - General, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Nos. 1-7, 1941 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Nos. 8-13, 1941 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Nos. 14-19, 1941 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Nos. 20-25, 1941 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Nos. 26-31, 1942 (Box-folder 8: 8)
- Notes, 1920-1940 (Box-folder 9: 1-30)
- Academic File, 1917-1976
  - Student career, 1917-1932
    - Lecture and reading notes, 1924-1930 (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
    - Papers, 1917-1922 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    - Ph.D thesis, 1931-1932
      - Drafts and fragments, 1931 (Box-folder 10: 4-7)
      - Complete, 1932 (Box-folder 11: 1-2)
    - Syllabus, 1929 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - Teaching career, 1930-1977
    - Correspondence, 1930-1976 (Box-folder 11: 4)
    - Course readers, 1970-1977 (Box-folder 11: 5-7, Box-folder 12: 1-5)
    - Course readers, 1977 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - Examination questions, assignments, and course requirements, 1963 (Box-folder 13: 2)
    - Lecture notes and outlines, 1935-1960 (Box-folder 13: 3)
    - Reports, 1937-1939 (Box-folder 13: 4)
    - Syllabi, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 13: 5-6)
- Subject File, 1933-1979
  - Advertising, 1940-1970 (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - Agriculture, 1942-1979 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - Alberta stamp scrip, 1935-1939 (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - Anti-poverty programs, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - Antitrust and monopolies, 1955-1979 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - Automobile insurance, 1937-1941 (Box-folder 14: 2)
  - Banking, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 14: 3)
  - Big business, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 14: 4)
  - Books, 1962-1979 (Box-folder 14: 5)
  - Bretton Woods agreement, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 14: 6)
  - Bureaucracy, 1940-1979 (Box-folder 14: 7)
  - California Club, 1943 (Box-folder 14: 8)
  - Civil rights, 1974 (Box-folder 14: 9)
  - Collectivism, 1950-1979 (Box-folder 14: 10)
  - Communism, 1954-1979 (Box-folder 14: 11)
  - Consumerism, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 14: 12)
  - Crime, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 14: 13)
  - Culture, 1972 (Box-folder 14: 14)
  - Disarmament, 1961-1975 (Box-folder 14: 15-16)
  - Education, 1943-1979 (Box-folder 14: 17)
  - Employment, 1943-1948 (Box-folder 14: 18)
  - Energy, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 14: 19)
  - Ethics, 1962-1979 (Box-folder 14: 20)
  - Family, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 14: 21)
  - Foreign aid, 1968-1979 (Box-folder 15: 1)
  - Foreign relations, 1950 (Box-folder 15: 2)
  - Foreign trade, 1943-1974 (Box-folder 15: 3-5)
  - Free enterprise, 1943-1979 (Box-folder 15: 6)
  - Freeman magazine, 1951 (Box-folder 15: 7)
  - Gold standard, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 15: 8)
  - Government ownership and regulation, 1943-1979 (Box-folder 15: 9)
  - Government spending, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 15: 10)
  - Great Britain, 1940-1979 (Box-folder 15: 11)
  - "Ham and Eggs" plan, 1938-1941 (Box-folder 15: 12-14)
    Relates to the old-age pension movement in California in the 1930s. Includes correspondence.
  - Health care and medicine, 1941-1979 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Housing, 1946 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - Income statistics, 1948-1976 (Box-folder 16: 3-4)
  - Industrial Revolution, 1968-1978 (Box-folder 16: 5)
  - Inflation, 1974 (Box-folder 16: 6)
  - Investments, 1976 (Box-folder 16: 7)
  - John Birch Society, 1961 (Box-folder 16: 8)
  - Keynes, John Maynard, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 16: 9)
  - Law, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 16: 10)
  - Minimum wage laws, 1948-1974 (Box-folder 16: 11-12)
  - National Recovery Administration, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 16: 13)
  - News media, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 16: 14)
  - Office of Price Administration, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 16: 15)
  - Optimism, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 16: 16)
  - Planning, 1942-1979 (Box-folder 16: 17)
  - Politics, 1936-1979 (Box-folder 16: 18, Box-folder 17: 1-4)
  - Pollution and environmentalism, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 17: 5)
  - Population and food, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 17: 6)
  - Price controls, 1941-1979 (Box-folder 17: 7)
  - Profits, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 17: 8)
  - Progress, 1976 (Box-folder 17: 9)
  - Psychology, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 17: 10)
  - Racism, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 17: 11)
  - Religion, 1953-1979 (Box-folder 17: 12-13)
  - Rising prices, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 17: 14)
  - Science, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 18: 1)
  - Segregation, 1955-1975 (Box-folder 18: 2-5)
  - Social security, 1950-1979 (Box-folder 18: 6-8)
  - Soviet Union, 1946-1979 (Box-folder 18: 9)
  - Taxes, 1943-1979 (Box-folder 19: 1)
  - Terrorism, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 19: 2)
  - Unemployment, 1955-1979 (Box-folder 19: 3)
  - Unions and labor relations, 1940-1979 (Box-folder 19: 4)
  - United Nations, 1955-1979 (Box-folder 19: 5)
  - Wages, 1939-1979 (Box-folder 19: 6)
  - Women's liberation, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 19: 7)
- Speeches and Writings by Others, 1927-1980
  - Adams, Claris, 1943 (Box-folder 19: 8)
  - Babson, David L., 1968 (Box-folder 19: 9)
  - Bleiberg, Robert M., 1975 (Box-folder 19: 10)
  - Borders, Irvin, 1946 (Box-folder 19: 11)
  - Byoir, Carl, 1942 (Box-folder 19: 12)
  - Carpenter, Wayne, 1971 (Box-folder 19: 13)
  - Carson, Clarence B., 1971 (Box-folder 19: 14)
  - Carver, T. N. (Thomas Nixon), 1935-1950 (Box-folder 19: 15)
  - Davenport, John A., 1975 (Box-folder 19: 16)
  - Friedman, Milton and George J. Stigler, 1946
    - "The Current Housing Problem: Ceilings or Roofs?," article drafts, 1946 (Box-folder 19: 17)
    - Editorial comments and correspondence, 1946 (Box-folder 20: 1)
      Includes letter from Ayn Rand to William C. Mullendore.
  - Fromm, Erich, 1973 (Box-folder 20: 2)
  - Harper, F. A., 1945 (Box-folder 20: 3)
  - Greenwald, David, 1966 (Box-folder 20: 4)
  - Harper, Roland M., 1939 (Box-folder 20: 5)
  - Hazlitt, Henry, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 20: 6)
  - Hoffman, Paul G., 1938-1943 (Box-folder 20: 7)
  - Hoiles, R. C., 1947 (Box-folder 20: 8)
  - Lage, Gerald M., 1973 (Box-folder 20: 9)
  - McCracken, Paul W., 1980 (Box-folder 20: 10)
  - Mowrer, O. Hobart, 1961 (Box-folder 20: 11)
  - Mullendore, William C., 1950-1951 (Box-folder 20: 12)
  - North, Gary, 1975 (Box-folder 20: 13)
  - Petro, Sylvester, 1964 (Box-folder 20: 14)
  - Read, Leonard, 1942 (Box-folder 20: 15)
  - Rorty, M. C., 1933 (Box-folder 20: 16)
  - Rose, Tom, 1975 (Box-folder 20: 17)
  - Summers, Brian, 1974 (Box-folder 20: 18)
  - Shafer, Ronald G., 1972 (Box-folder 20: 19)
  - Szasz, Thomas S., 1961-1967 (Box-folder 20: 20)
  - Terborgh, G. W., 1929 (Box-folder 20: 21)
  - Tibbetts, Carleton B., 1942 (Box-folder 20: 22)
  - Tugwell, Rexford G., 1927-1935 (Box-folder 20: 23)
- Graphic Materials, 1922, 1938
  - Cartoons for Why Are We So Prosperous?, 1938 (Box-folder 20: 24)
  - Photographs depicting Dorothy Lowe, 1922 (Box-folder 20: 25)
- Printed Matter, 1929-1979
  - Monographs, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 21: 1-14)
  - Pamphlets, 1929-1976 (Box-folder 22: 1-58, Box-folder 23: 1-76)
  - Serial issues, 1942-1979 (Box-folder 24: 1-42)